The third way to fight deadlocks that
is left is to avoid the hold and wait.
Simply put, we can devise a solution in which
philosophers agree on who is going to eat
next rather than on who gets a certain chopstick.
You have such an approach presented here: we have
one semaphore per philosopher, an extra semaphore
called mutex, and an array of size n of states.
One state can either be
HUNGRY, THINKING, or EATING.
To enter and exit the critical section
we have two methods: enterCS and exitCS.
In the enterCS method, each philosopher waits on
the shared mutex variable. In other words, only
one philosopher at a time can run the following
two instructions, which change his/her state to
HUNGRY and call the help method.
After calling signal on mutex,
the philosopher running the entryCS method starts
waiting for a signal on its entry of the S array.
So, how does the help function work?
Only if the philosopher invoking it
is hungry and his/her neighbors are not eating,
then it changes the state of the philosopher
invoking it to eating and sends a signal to it.
Notice that since help runs in between a wait and
signal on the shared variable mutex, if multiple
neighboring philosophers try to change their state
from HUNGRY to EATING, only one manages to do so.
Once a philosopher is done eating, then he/she
runs the exitCS method. Again, the relevant
instructions are run inside a wait/signal
on the shared variable mutex.
In this case, the philosopher
sets his/her state to THINKING and then helps
his/her neighbors, trying to send them a signal
they can use to enter their critical
section (assuming they indeed want to).
This solution is valid when
it comes to mutual exclusion,
and it also avoids deadlocks.
nonetheless, a process can starve.
As done before, try to reason
formally about these properties.
If you are interested in a
solution that also ensures
fairness, you can find a paper
discussing it in the attached link.